CHAPTER XLIII.
ELIZABETH, as they drove along, watched for the first appearance of Pemberley Woods with
some perturbation; and when at length they turned in at the lodge, her spirits were in
a high flutter.
The park was very large, and contained great variety of ground.
They entered it in one of its lowest points, and drove for some time through a beautiful
wood stretching over a wide extent.
Elizabeth’s mind was too full for conversation, but she saw and admired every remarkable spot
and point of view.
They gradually ascended for half a mile, and then found themselves at the top of a considerable
eminence, where the wood ceased, and the eye was instantly caught by Pemberley House, situated
on the opposite side of the valley, into which the road with some abruptness wound.
It was a large, handsome stone building, standing well on rising ground, and backed by a ridge
of high woody hills; and in front a stream of some natural importance was swelled into
greater, but without any artificial appearance.
Its banks were neither formal nor falsely adorned.
Elizabeth was delighted.
She had never seen a place for which nature had done more, or where natural beauty had
been so little counteracted by an awkward taste.
They were all of them warm in their admiration; and at that moment she felt that to be mistress
of Pemberley might be something!
They descended the hill, crossed the bridge, and drove to the door; and, while examining
the nearer aspect of the house, all her apprehension of meeting its owner returned.
She dreaded lest the chambermaid had been mistaken.
On applying to see the place, they were admitted into the hall; and Elizabeth, as they waited
for the housekeeper, had leisure to wonder at her being where she was.
The housekeeper came; a respectable looking elderly woman, much less fine, and more civil,
than she had any notion of finding her.
They followed her into the dining-parlour.
It was a large, well-proportioned room, handsomely fitted up.
Elizabeth, after slightly surveying it, went to a window to enjoy its prospect.
The hill, crowned with wood, from which they had descended, receiving increased abruptness
from the distance, was a beautiful object.
Every disposition of the ground was good; and she looked on the whole scene, the river,
the trees scattered on its banks, and the winding of the valley, as far as she could
trace it, with delight.
As they passed into other rooms, these objects were taking different positions; but from
every window there were beauties to be seen.
The rooms were lofty and handsome, and their furniture suitable to the fortune of their
proprietor; but Elizabeth saw, with admiration of his taste, that it was neither gaudy nor
uselessly fine,—with less of splendour, and more real elegance, than the furniture
of Rosings.
“And of this place,” thought she, “I might have been mistress!
With these rooms I might have now been familiarly acquainted!
Instead of viewing them as a stranger, I might have rejoiced in them as my own, and welcomed
to them as visitors my uncle and aunt.
But, no,” recollecting herself, “that could never be; my uncle and aunt would have
been lost to me; I should not have been allowed to invite them.”
This was a lucky recollection—it saved her from something like regret.
She longed to inquire of the housekeeper whether her master were really absent, but had not
courage for it.
At length, however, the question was asked by her uncle; and she turned away with alarm,
while Mrs. Reynolds replied, that he was; adding, “But we expect him to-morrow, with
a large party of friends.”
How rejoiced was Elizabeth that their own journey had not by any circumstance been delayed
a day!
Her aunt now called her to look at a picture.
She approached, and saw the likeness of Mr. Wickham, suspended, amongst several other
miniatures, over the mantel-piece.
Her aunt asked her, smilingly, how she liked it.
The housekeeper came forward, and told them it was the picture of a young gentleman, the
son of her late master’s steward, who had been brought up by him at his own expense.
“He is now gone into the army,” she added; “but I am afraid he has turned out very
wild.”
Mrs. Gardiner looked at her niece with a smile, but Elizabeth could not return it.
“And that,” said Mrs. Reynolds, pointing to another of the miniatures, “is my master—and
very like him.
It was drawn at the same time as the other—about eight years ago.”
“I have heard much of your master’s fine person,” said Mrs. Gardiner, looking at
the picture; “it is a handsome face.
But, Lizzy, you can tell us whether it is like or not.”
Mrs. Reynolds’ respect for Elizabeth seemed to increase on this intimation of her knowing
her master.
“Does that young lady know Mr. Darcy?”
Elizabeth coloured, and said, “A little.”
“And do not you think him a very handsome gentleman, ma’am?”
“Yes, very handsome.”
“I am sure I know none so handsome; but in the gallery upstairs you will see a finer,
larger picture of him than this.
This room was my late master’s favourite room, and these miniatures are just as they
used to be then.
He was very fond of them.”
This accounted to Elizabeth for Mr. Wickham’s being among them.
Mrs. Reynolds then directed their attention to one of Miss Darcy, drawn when she was only
eight years old.
“And is Miss Darcy as handsome as her brother?” said Mr. Gardiner.
“Oh, yes—the handsomest young lady that ever was seen; and so accomplished!
She plays and sings all day long.
In the next room is a new instrument just come down for her—a present from my master:
she comes here to-morrow with him.”
Mr. Gardiner, whose manners were easy and pleasant, encouraged her communicativeness
by his questions and remarks: Mrs. Reynolds, either from pride or attachment, had evidently
great pleasure in talking of her master and his sister.
“Is your master much at Pemberley in the course of the year?”
“Not so much as I could wish, sir: but I dare say he may spend half his time here;
and Miss Darcy is always down for the summer months.”
“Except,” thought Elizabeth, “when she goes to Ramsgate.”
“If your master would marry, you might see more of him.”
“Yes, sir; but I do not know when that will be.
I do not know who is good enough for him.”
Mr. and Mrs. Gardiner smiled.
Elizabeth could not help saying, “It is very much to his credit, I am sure, that you
should think so.”
“I say no more than the truth, and what everybody will say that knows him,” replied
the other.
Elizabeth thought this was going pretty far; and she listened with increasing astonishment
as the housekeeper added, “I have never had a cross word from him in my life, and
I have known him ever since he was four years old.”
This was praise of all others most extraordinary, most opposite to her ideas.
That he was not a good-tempered man had been her firmest opinion.
Her keenest attention was awakened: she longed to hear more; and was grateful to her uncle
for saying,— “There are very few people of whom so much
can be said.
You are lucky in having such a master.”
“Yes, sir, I know I am.
If I were to go through the world, I could not meet with a better.
But I have always observed, that they who are good-natured when children, are good-natured
when they grow up; and he was always the sweetest tempered, most generous-hearted boy in the
world.”
Elizabeth almost stared at her.
“Can this be Mr. Darcy?”
thought she.
“His father was an excellent man,” said Mrs. Gardiner.
“Yes, ma’am, that he was indeed; and his son will be just like him—just as affable
to the poor.”
Elizabeth listened, wondered, doubted, and was impatient for more.
Mrs. Reynolds could interest her on no other point.
She related the subjects of the pictures, the dimensions of the rooms, and the price
of the furniture in vain.
Mr. Gardiner, highly amused by the kind of family prejudice, to which he attributed her
excessive commendation of her master, soon led again to the subject; and she dwelt with
energy on his many merits, as they proceeded together up the great staircase.
“He is the best landlord, and the best master,” said she, “that ever lived.
Not like the wild young men now-a-days, who think of nothing but themselves.
There is not one of his tenants or servants but what will give him a good name.
Some people call him proud; but I am sure I never saw anything of it.
To my fancy, it is only because he does not rattle away like other young men.”
“In what an amiable light does this place him!”
thought Elizabeth.
“This fine account of him,” whispered her aunt as they walked, “is not quite consistent
with his behaviour to our poor friend.”
“Perhaps we might be deceived.”
“That is not very likely; our authority was too good.”
On reaching the spacious lobby above, they were shown into a very pretty sitting-room,
lately fitted up with greater elegance and lightness than the apartments below; and were
informed that it was but just done to give pleasure to Miss Darcy, who had taken a liking
to the room, when last at Pemberley.
“He is certainly a good brother,” said Elizabeth, as she walked towards one of the
windows.
Mrs. Reynolds anticipated Miss Darcy’s delight, when she should enter the room.
“And this is always the way with him,” she added.
“Whatever can give his sister any pleasure, is sure to be done in a moment.
There is nothing he would not do for her.”
The picture gallery, and two or three of the principal bed-rooms, were all that remained
to be shown.
In the former were many good paintings: but Elizabeth knew nothing of the art; and from
such as had been already visible below, she had willingly turned to look at some drawings
of Miss Darcy’s, in crayons, whose subjects were usually more interesting, and also more
intelligible.
In the gallery there were many family portraits, but they could have little to fix the attention
of a stranger.
Elizabeth walked on in quest of the only face whose features would be known to her.
At last it arrested her—and she beheld a striking resemblance of Mr. Darcy, with such
a smile over the face, as she remembered to have sometimes seen, when he looked at her.
She stood several minutes before the picture, in earnest contemplation, and returned to
it again before they quitted the gallery.
Mrs. Reynolds informed them, that it had been taken in his father’s lifetime.
There was certainly at this moment, in Elizabeth’s mind, a more gentle sensation towards the
original than she had ever felt in the height of their acquaintance.
The commendation bestowed on him by Mrs. Reynolds was of no trifling nature.
What praise is more valuable than the praise of an intelligent servant?
As a brother, a landlord, a master, she considered how many people’s happiness were in his
guardianship!
How much of pleasure or pain it was in his power to bestow!
How much of good or evil must be done by him!
Every idea that had been brought forward by the housekeeper was favourable to his character;
and as she stood before the canvas, on which he was represented, and fixed his eyes upon
herself, she thought of his regard with a deeper sentiment of gratitude than it had
ever raised before: she remembered its warmth, and softened its impropriety of expression.
When all of the house that was open to general inspection had been seen, they returned down
stairs; and, taking leave of the housekeeper, were consigned over to the gardener, who met
them at the hall door.
As they walked across the lawn towards the river, Elizabeth turned back to look again;
her uncle and aunt stopped also; and while the former was conjecturing as to the date
of the building, the owner of it himself suddenly came forward from the road which led behind
it to the stables.
They were within twenty yards of each other; and so abrupt was his appearance, that it
was impossible to avoid his sight.
Their eyes instantly met, and the cheeks of each were overspread with the deepest blush.
He absolutely started, and for a moment seemed immovable from surprise; but shortly recovering
himself, advanced towards the party, and spoke to Elizabeth, if not in terms of perfect composure,
at least of perfect civility.
She had instinctively turned away; but stopping on his approach, received his compliments
with an embarrassment impossible to be overcome.
Had his first appearance, or his resemblance to the picture they had just been examining,
been insufficient to assure the other two that they now saw Mr. Darcy, the gardener’s
expression of surprise, on beholding his master, must immediately have told it.
They stood a little aloof while he was talking to their niece, who, astonished and confused,
scarcely dared lift her eyes to his face, and knew not what answer she returned to his
civil inquiries after her family.
Amazed at the alteration of his manner since they last parted, every sentence that he uttered
was increasing her embarrassment; and every idea of the impropriety of her being found
there recurring to her mind, the few minutes in which they continued together were some
of the most uncomfortable of her life.
Nor did he seem much more at ease; when he spoke, his accent had none of its usual sedateness;
and he repeated his inquiries as to the time of her having left Longbourn, and of her stay
in Derbyshire, so often, and in so hurried a way, as plainly spoke the distraction of
his thoughts.
At length, every idea seemed to fail him; and after standing a few moments without saying
a word, he suddenly recollected himself, and took leave.
The others then joined her, and expressed their admiration of his figure; but Elizabeth
heard not a word, and, wholly engrossed by her own feelings, followed them in silence.
She was overpowered by shame and vexation.
Her coming there was the most unfortunate, the most ill-judged thing in the world!
How strange must it appear to him!
In what a disgraceful light might it not strike so vain a man!
It might seem as if she had purposely thrown herself in his way again!
Oh!
why did she come? or, why did he thus come a day before he was expected?
Had they been only ten minutes sooner, they should have been beyond the reach of his discrimination;
for it was plain that he was that moment arrived, that moment alighted from his horse or his
carriage.
She blushed again and again over the perverseness of the meeting.
And his behaviour, so strikingly altered,—what could it mean?
That he should even speak to her was amazing!—but to speak with such civility, to inquire after
her family!
Never in her life had she seen his manners so little dignified, never had he spoken with
such gentleness as on this unexpected meeting.
What a contrast did it offer to his last address in Rosings Park, when he put his letter into
her hand!
She knew not what to think, or how to account for it.
They had now entered a beautiful walk by the side of the water, and every step was bringing
forward a nobler fall of ground, or a finer reach of the woods to which they were approaching:
but it was some time before Elizabeth was sensible of any of it; and, though she answered
mechanically to the repeated appeals of her uncle and aunt, and seemed to direct her eyes
to such objects as they pointed out, she distinguished no part of the scene.
Her thoughts were all fixed on that one spot of Pemberley House, whichever it might be,
where Mr. Darcy then was.
She longed to know what at that moment was passing in his mind; in what manner he thought
of her, and whether, in defiance of everything, she was still dear to him.
Perhaps he had been civil only because he felt himself at ease; yet there had been that
in his voice, which was not like ease.
Whether he had felt more of pain or of pleasure in seeing her, she could not tell, but he
certainly had not seen her with composure.
At length, however, the remarks of her companions on her absence of mind roused her, and she
felt the necessity of appearing more like herself.
They entered the woods, and, bidding adieu to the river for a while, ascended some of
the higher grounds; whence, in spots where the opening of the trees gave the eye power
to wander, were many charming views of the valley, the opposite hills, with the long
range of woods overspreading many, and occasionally part of the stream.
Mr. Gardiner expressed a wish of going round the whole park, but feared it might be beyond
a walk.
With a triumphant smile, they were told, that it was ten miles round.
It settled the matter; and they pursued the accustomed circuit; which brought them again,
after some time, in a descent among hanging woods, to the edge of the water, and one of
its narrowest parts.
They crossed it by a simple bridge, in character with the general air of the scene: it was
a spot less adorned than any they had yet visited; and the valley, here contracted into
a glen, allowed room only for the stream, and a narrow walk amidst the rough coppice-wood
which bordered it.
Elizabeth longed to explore its windings; but when they had crossed the bridge, and
perceived their distance from the house, Mrs. Gardiner, who was not a great walker, could
go no farther, and thought only of returning to the carriage as quickly as possible.
Her niece was, therefore, obliged to submit, and they took their way towards the house
on the opposite side of the river, in the nearest direction; but their progress was
slow, for Mr. Gardiner, though seldom able to indulge the taste, was very fond of fishing,
and was so much engaged in watching the occasional appearance of some trout in the water, and
talking to the man about them, that he advanced but little.
Whilst wandering on in this slow manner, they were again surprised, and Elizabeth’s astonishment
was quite equal to what it had been at first, by the sight of Mr. Darcy approaching them,
and at no great distance.
The walk being here less sheltered than on the other side, allowed them to see him before
they met.
Elizabeth, however astonished, was at least more prepared for an interview than before,
and resolved to appear and to speak with calmness, if he really intended to meet them.
For a few moments, indeed, she felt that he would probably strike into some other path.
The idea lasted while a turning in the walk concealed him from their view; the turning
past, he was immediately before them.
With a glance she saw that he had lost none of his recent civility; and, to imitate his
politeness, she began as they met to admire the beauty of the place; but she had not got
beyond the words “delightful,” and “charming,” when some unlucky recollections obtruded,
and she fancied that praise of Pemberley from her might be mischievously construed.
Her colour changed, and she said no more.
Mrs. Gardiner was standing a little behind; and on her pausing, he asked her if she would
do him the honour of introducing him to her friends.
This was a stroke of civility for which she was quite unprepared; and she could hardly
suppress a smile at his being now seeking the acquaintance of some of those very people,
against whom his pride had revolted, in his offer to herself.
“What will be his surprise,” thought she, “when he knows who they are!
He takes them now for people of fashion.”
The introduction, however, was immediately made; and as she named their relationship
to herself, she stole a sly look at him, to see how he bore it; and was not without the
expectation of his decamping as fast as he could from such disgraceful companions.
That he was surprised by the connection was evident: he sustained it, however, with fortitude:
and, so far from going away, turned back with them, and entered into conversation with Mr.
Gardiner.
Elizabeth could not but be pleased, could not but triumph.
It was consoling that he should know she had some relations for whom there was no need
to blush.
She listened most attentively to all that passed between them, and gloried in every
expression, every sentence of her uncle, which marked his intelligence, his taste, or his
good manners.
The conversation soon turned upon fishing; and she heard Mr. Darcy invite him, with the
greatest civility, to fish there as often as he chose, while he continued in the neighbourhood,
offering at the same time to supply him with fishing tackle, and pointing out those parts
of the stream where there was usually most sport.
Mrs. Gardiner, who was walking arm in arm with Elizabeth, gave her a look expressive
of her wonder.
Elizabeth said nothing, but it gratified her exceedingly; the compliment must be all for
herself.
Her astonishment, however, was extreme; and continually was she repeating, “Why is he
so altered?
From what can it proceed?
It cannot be for me, it cannot be for my sake that his manners are thus softened.
My reproofs at Hunsford could not work such a change as this.
It is impossible that he should still love me.”
After walking some time in this way, the two ladies in front, the two gentlemen behind,
on resuming their places, after descending to the brink of the river for the better inspection
of some curious water-plant, there chanced to be a little alteration.
It originated in Mrs. Gardiner, who, fatigued by the exercise of the morning, found Elizabeth’s
arm inadequate to her support, and consequently preferred her husband’s.
Mr. Darcy took her place by her niece, and they walked on together.
After a short silence the lady first spoke.
She wished him to know that she had been assured of his absence before she came to the place,
and accordingly began by observing, that his arrival had been very unexpected—“for
your housekeeper,” she added, “informed us that you would certainly not be here till
to-morrow; and, indeed, before we left Bakewell, we understood that you were not immediately
expected in the country.”
He acknowledged the truth of it all; and said that business with his steward had occasioned
his coming forward a few hours before the rest of the party with whom he had been travelling.
“They will join me early to-morrow,” he continued, “and among them are some who
will claim an acquaintance with you,—Mr. Bingley and his sisters.”
Elizabeth answered only by a slight bow.
Her thoughts were instantly driven back to the time when Mr. Bingley’s name had been
last mentioned between them; and if she might judge from his complexion, his mind was not
very differently engaged.
“There is also one other person in the party,” he continued after a pause, “who more particularly
wishes to be known to you.
Will you allow me, or do I ask too much, to introduce my sister to your acquaintance during
your stay at Lambton?”
The surprise of such an application was great indeed; it was too great for her to know in
what manner she acceded to it.
She immediately felt that whatever desire Miss Darcy might have of being acquainted
with her, must be the work of her brother, and without looking farther, it was satisfactory;
it was gratifying to know that his resentment had not made him think really ill of her.
They now walked on in silence; each of them deep in thought.
Elizabeth was not comfortable; that was impossible; but she was flattered and pleased.
His wish of introducing his sister to her was a compliment of the highest kind.
They soon outstripped the others; and when they had reached the carriage, Mr. and Mrs.
Gardiner were half a quarter of a mile behind.
He then asked her to walk into the house—but she declared herself not tired, and they stood
together on the lawn.
At such a time much might have been said, and silence was very awkward.
She wanted to talk, but there seemed an embargo on every subject.
At last she recollected that she had been travelling, and they talked of Matlock and
Dovedale with great perseverance.
Yet time and her aunt moved slowly—and her patience and her ideas were nearly worn out
before the tête-à-tête was over.
On Mr. and Mrs. Gardiner’s coming up they were all pressed to go into the house and
take some refreshment; but this was declined, and they parted on each side with the utmost
politeness.
Mr. Darcy handed the ladies into the carriage; and when it drove off, Elizabeth saw him walking
slowly towards the house.
The observations of her uncle and aunt now began; and each of them pronounced him to
be infinitely superior to anything they had expected.
“He is perfectly well-behaved, polite, and unassuming,” said her uncle.
“There is something a little stately in him, to be sure,” replied her aunt; “but
it is confined to his air, and is not unbecoming.
I can now say with the housekeeper, that though some people may call him proud, I have seen
nothing of it.”
“I was never more surprised than by his behaviour to us.
It was more than civil; it was really attentive; and there was no necessity for such attention.
His acquaintance with Elizabeth was very trifling.”
“To be sure, Lizzy,” said her aunt, “he is not so handsome as Wickham; or rather he
has not Wickham’s countenance, for his features are perfectly good.
But how came you to tell us that he was so disagreeable?”
Elizabeth excused herself as well as she could: said that she had liked him better when they
met in Kent than before, and that she had never seen him so pleasant as this morning.
“But perhaps he may be a little whimsical in his civilities,” replied her uncle.
“Your great men often are; and therefore I shall not take him at his word about fishing,
as he might change his mind another day, and warn me off his grounds.”
Elizabeth felt that they had entirely mistaken his character, but said nothing.
“From what we have seen of him,” continued Mrs. Gardiner, “I really should not have
thought that he could have behaved in so cruel a way by anybody as he has done by poor Wickham.
He has not an ill-natured look.
On the contrary, there is something pleasing about his mouth when he speaks.
And there is something of dignity in his countenance, that would not give one an unfavourable idea
of his heart.
But, to be sure, the good lady who showed us the house did give him a most flaming character!
I could hardly help laughing aloud sometimes.
But he is a liberal master, I suppose, and that, in the eye of a servant, comprehends
every virtue.”
Elizabeth here felt herself called on to say something in vindication of his behaviour
to Wickham; and, therefore, gave them to understand, in as guarded a manner as she could, that
by what she had heard from his relations in Kent, his actions were capable of a very different
construction; and that his character was by no means so faulty, nor Wickham’s so amiable,
as they had been considered in Hertfordshire.
In confirmation of this, she related the particulars of all the pecuniary transactions in which
they had been connected, without actually naming her authority, but stating it to be
such as might be relied on.
Mrs. Gardiner was surprised and concerned: but as they were now approaching the scene
of her former pleasures, every idea gave way to the charm of recollection; and she was
too much engaged in pointing out to her husband all the interesting spots in its environs,
to think of anything else.
Fatigued as she had been by the morning’s walk, they had no sooner dined than she set
off again in quest of her former acquaintance, and the evening was spent in the satisfactions
of an intercourse renewed after many years’ discontinuance.
The occurrences of the day were too full of interest to leave Elizabeth much attention
for any of these new friends; and she could do nothing but think, and think with wonder,
of Mr. Darcy’s civility, and, above all, of his wishing her to be acquainted with his
sister.
CHAPTER XLIV.
ELIZABETH had settled it that Mr. Darcy would bring his sister to visit her the very day
after her reaching Pemberley; and was, consequently, resolved not to be out of sight of the inn
the whole of that morning.
But her conclusion was false; for on the very morning after their own arrival at Lambton
these visitors came.
They had been walking about the place with some of their new friends, and were just returned
to the inn to dress themselves for dining with the same family, when the sound of a
carriage drew them to a window, and they saw a gentleman and lady in a curricle driving
up the street.
Elizabeth, immediately recognizing the livery, guessed what it meant, and imparted no small
degree of surprise to her relations, by acquainting them with the honour which she expected.
Her uncle and aunt were all amazement; and the embarrassment of her manner as she spoke,
joined to the circumstance itself, and many of the circumstances of the preceding day,
opened to them a new idea on the business.
Nothing had ever suggested it before, but they now felt that there was no other way
of accounting for such attentions from such a quarter than by supposing a partiality for
their niece.
While these newly-born notions were passing in their heads, the perturbation of Elizabeth’s
feelings was every moment increasing.
She was quite amazed at her own discomposure; but, amongst other causes of disquiet, she
dreaded lest the partiality of the brother should have said too much in her favour; and,
more than commonly anxious to please, she naturally suspected that every power of pleasing
would fail her.
She retreated from the window, fearful of being seen; and as she walked up and down
the room, endeavouring to compose herself, saw such looks of inquiring surprise in her
uncle and aunt as made everything worse.
Miss Darcy and her brother appeared, and this formidable introduction took place.
With astonishment did Elizabeth see that her new acquaintance was at least as much embarrassed
as herself.
Since her being at Lambton, she had heard that Miss Darcy was exceedingly proud; but
the observation of a very few minutes convinced her that she was only exceedingly shy.
She found it difficult to obtain even a word from her beyond a monosyllable.
Miss Darcy was tall, and on a larger scale than Elizabeth; and, though little more than
sixteen, her figure was formed, and her appearance womanly and graceful.
She was less handsome than her brother, but there was sense and good-humour in her face,
and her manners were perfectly unassuming and gentle.
Elizabeth, who had expected to find in her as acute and unembarrassed an observer as
ever Mr. Darcy had been, was much relieved by discerning such different feelings.
They had not been long together before Darcy told her that Bingley was also coming to wait
on her; and she had barely time to express her satisfaction, and prepare for such a visitor,
when Bingley’s quick step was heard on the stairs, and in a moment he entered the room.
All Elizabeth’s anger against him had been long done away; but had she still felt any,
it could hardly have stood its ground against the unaffected cordiality with which he expressed
himself on seeing her again.
He inquired in a friendly, though general, way, after her family, and looked and spoke
with the same good-humoured ease that he had ever done.
To Mr. and Mrs. Gardiner he was scarcely a less interesting personage than to herself.
They had long wished to see him.
The whole party before them, indeed, excited a lively attention.
The suspicions which had just arisen of Mr. Darcy and their niece, directed their observation
towards each with an earnest, though guarded, inquiry; and they soon drew from those inquiries
the full conviction that one of them at least knew what it was to love.
Of the lady’s sensations they remained a little in doubt; but that the gentleman was
overflowing with admiration was evident enough.
Elizabeth, on her side, had much to do.
She wanted to ascertain the feelings of each of her visitors, she wanted to compose her
own, and to make herself agreeable to all; and in the latter object, where she feared
most to fail, she was most sure of success, for those to whom she endeavoured to give
pleasure were pre-possessed in her favour.
Bingley was ready, Georgiana was eager, and Darcy determined, to be pleased.
In seeing Bingley, her thoughts naturally flew to her sister; and oh!
how ardently did she long to know whether any of his were directed in a like manner.
Sometimes she could fancy that he talked less than on former occasions, and once or twice
pleased herself with the notion that, as he looked at her, he was trying to trace a resemblance.
But, though this might be imaginary, she could not be deceived as to his behaviour to Miss
Darcy, who had been set up as a rival to Jane.
No look appeared on either side that spoke particular regard.
Nothing occurred between them that could justify the hopes of his sister.
On this point she was soon satisfied; and two or three little circumstances occurred
ere they parted, which, in her anxious interpretation, denoted a recollection of Jane, not untinctured
by tenderness, and a wish of saying more that might lead to the mention of her, had he dared.
He observed to her, at a moment when the others were talking together, and in a tone which
had something of real regret, that it “was a very long time since he had had the pleasure
of seeing her;” and, before she could reply, he added, “It is above eight months.
We have not met since the 26th of November, when we were all dancing together at Netherfield.”
Elizabeth was pleased to find his memory so exact; and he afterwards took occasion to
ask her, when unattended to by any of the rest, whether all her sisters were at Longbourn.
There was not much in the question, nor in the preceding remark; but there was a look
and a manner which gave them meaning.
It was not often that she could turn her eyes on Mr. Darcy himself; but whenever she did
catch a glimpse she saw an expression of general complaisance, and in all that he said, she
heard an accent so far removed from hauteur or disdain of his companions, as convinced
her that the improvement of manners which she had yesterday witnessed, however temporary
its existence might prove, had at least outlived one day.
When she saw him thus seeking the acquaintance, and courting the good opinion of people with
whom any intercourse a few months ago would have been a disgrace; when she saw him thus
civil, not only to herself, but to the very relations whom he had openly disdained, and
recollected their last lively scene in Hunsford Parsonage, the difference, the change was
so great, and struck so forcibly on her mind, that she could hardly restrain her astonishment
from being visible.
Never, even in the company of his dear friends at Netherfield, or his dignified relations
at Rosings, had she seen him so desirous to please, so free from self-consequence or unbending
reserve, as now, when no importance could result from the success of his endeavours,
and when even the acquaintance of those to whom his attentions were addressed, would
draw down the ridicule and censure of the ladies both of Netherfield and Rosings.
Their visitors stayed with them above half an hour; and when they arose to depart, Mr.
Darcy called on his sister to join him in expressing their wish of seeing Mr. and Mrs.
Gardiner, and Miss Bennet, to dinner at Pemberley, before they left the country.
Miss Darcy, though with a diffidence which marked her little in the habit of giving invitations,
readily obeyed.
Mrs. Gardiner looked at her niece, desirous of knowing how she, whom the invitation most
concerned, felt disposed as to its acceptance, but Elizabeth had turned away her head.
Presuming, however, that this studied avoidance spoke rather a momentary embarrassment than
any dislike of the proposal, and seeing in her husband, who was fond of society, a perfect
willingness to accept it, she ventured to engage for her attendance, and the day after
the next was fixed on.
Bingley expressed great pleasure in the certainty of seeing Elizabeth again, having still a
great deal to say to her, and many inquiries to make after all their Hertfordshire friends.
Elizabeth, construing all this into a wish of hearing her speak of her sister, was pleased;
and on this account, as well as some others, found herself, when their visitors left them,
capable of considering the last half hour with some satisfaction, though while it was
passing the enjoyment of it had been little.
Eager to be alone, and fearful of inquiries or hints from her uncle and aunt, she stayed
with them only long enough to hear their favourable opinion of Bingley, and then hurried away
to dress.
But she had no reason to fear Mr. and Mrs. Gardiner’s curiosity; it was not their wish
to force her communication.
It was evident that she was much better acquainted with Mr. Darcy than they had before any idea
of; it was evident that he was very much in love with her.
They saw much to interest, but nothing to justify inquiry.
Of Mr. Darcy it was now a matter of anxiety to think well; and, as far as their acquaintance
reached, there was no fault to find.
They could not be untouched by his politeness; and had they drawn his character from their
own feelings and his servant’s report, without any reference to any other account, the circle
in Hertfordshire to which he was known would not have recognized it for Mr. Darcy.
There was now an interest, however, in believing the housekeeper; and they soon became sensible
that the authority of a servant, who had known him since he was four years old, and whose
own manners indicated respectability, was not to be hastily rejected.
Neither had anything occurred in the intelligence of their Lambton friends that could materially
lessen its weight.
They had nothing to accuse him of but pride; pride he probably had, and if not, it would
certainly be imputed by the inhabitants of a small market town where the family did not
visit.
It was acknowledged, however, that he was a liberal man, and did much good among the
poor.
With respect to Wickham, the travellers soon found that he was not held there in much estimation;
for though the chief of his concerns with the son of his patron were imperfectly understood,
it was yet a well-known fact that, on his quitting Derbyshire, he had left many debts
behind him, which Mr. Darcy afterwards discharged.
As for Elizabeth, her thoughts were at Pemberley this evening more than the last; and the evening,
though as it passed it seemed long, was not long enough to determine her feelings towards
one in that mansion; and she lay awake two whole hours, endeavouring to make them out.
She certainly did not hate him.
No; hatred had vanished long ago, and she had almost as long been ashamed of ever feeling
a dislike against him, that could be so called.
The respect created by the conviction of his valuable qualities, though at first unwillingly
admitted, had for some time ceased to be repugnant to her feelings; and it was now heightened
into somewhat of a friendlier nature by the testimony so highly in his favour, and bringing
forward his disposition in so amiable a light, which yesterday had produced.
But above all, above respect and esteem, there was a motive within her of good-will which
could not be overlooked.
It was gratitude;—gratitude, not merely for having once loved her, but for loving
her still well enough to forgive all the petulance and acrimony of her manner in rejecting him,
and all the unjust accusations accompanying her rejection.
He who, she had been persuaded, would avoid her as his greatest enemy, seemed, on this
accidental meeting, most eager to preserve the acquaintance; and without any indelicate
display of regard, or any peculiarity of manner, where their two selves only were concerned,
was soliciting the good opinion of her friends, and bent on making her known to his sister.
Such a change in a man of so much pride excited not only astonishment but gratitude—for
to love, ardent love, it must be attributed; and, as such, its impression on her was of
a sort to be encouraged, as by no means unpleasing, though it could not be exactly defined.
She respected, she esteemed, she was grateful to him, she felt a real interest in his welfare;
and she only wanted to know how far she wished that welfare to depend upon herself, and how
far it would be for the happiness of both that she should employ the power, which her
fancy told her she still possessed, of bringing on the renewal of his addresses.
It had been settled in the evening, between the aunt and niece, that such a striking civility
as Miss Darcy’s, in coming to them on the very day of her arrival at Pemberley—for
she had reached it only to a late breakfast—ought to be imitated, though it could not be equalled,
by some exertion of politeness on their side; and, consequently, that it would be highly
expedient to wait on her at Pemberley the following morning.
They were, therefore, to go.
Elizabeth was pleased; though when she asked herself the reason, she had very little to
say in reply.
Mr. Gardiner left them soon after breakfast.
The fishing scheme had been renewed the day before, and a positive engagement made of
his meeting some of the gentlemen at Pemberley by noon.
CHAPTER XLV.
CONVINCED as Elizabeth now was that Miss Bingley’s dislike of her had originated in jealousy,
she could not help feeling how very unwelcome her appearance at Pemberley must be to her,
and was curious to know with how much civility on that lady’s side the acquaintance would
now be renewed.
On reaching the house, they were shown through the hall into the saloon, whose northern aspect
rendered it delightful for summer.
Its windows, opening to the ground, admitted a most refreshing view of the high woody hills
behind the house, and of the beautiful oaks and Spanish chestnuts which were scattered
over the intermediate lawn.
In this room they were received by Miss Darcy, who was sitting there with Mrs. Hurst and
Miss Bingley, and the lady with whom she lived in London.
Georgiana’s reception of them was very civil, but attended with all that embarrassment which,
though proceeding from shyness and the fear of doing wrong, would easily give to those
who felt themselves inferior the belief of her being proud and reserved.
Mrs. Gardiner and her niece, however, did her justice, and pitied her.
By Mrs. Hurst and Miss Bingley they were noticed only by a courtesy; and on their being seated,
a pause, awkward as such pauses must always be, succeeded for a few moments.
It was first broken by Mrs. Annesley, a genteel, agreeable-looking woman, whose endeavour to
introduce some kind of discourse proved her to be more truly well-bred than either of
the others; and between her and Mrs. Gardiner, with occasional help from Elizabeth, the conversation
was carried on.
Miss Darcy looked as if she wished for courage enough to join in it; and sometimes did venture
a short sentence, when there was least danger of its being heard.
Elizabeth soon saw that she was herself closely watched by Miss Bingley, and that she could
not speak a word, especially to Miss Darcy, without calling her attention.
This observation would not have prevented her from trying to talk to the latter, had
they not been seated at an inconvenient distance; but she was not sorry to be spared the necessity
of saying much: her own thoughts were employing her.
She expected every moment that some of the gentlemen would enter the room: she wished,
she feared, that the master of the house might be amongst them; and whether she wished or
feared it most, she could scarcely determine.
After sitting in this manner a quarter of an hour, without hearing Miss Bingley’s
voice, Elizabeth was roused by receiving from her a cold inquiry after the health of her
family.
She answered with equal indifference and brevity, and the other said no more.
The next variation which their visit afforded was produced by the entrance of servants with
cold meat, cake, and a variety of all the finest fruits in season; but this did not
take place till after many a significant look and smile from Mrs. Annesley to Miss Darcy
had been given, to remind her of her post.
There was now employment for the whole party; for though they could not all talk, they could
all eat; and the beautiful pyramids of grapes, nectarines, and peaches, soon collected them
round the table.
While thus engaged, Elizabeth had a fair opportunity of deciding whether she most feared or wished
for the appearance of Mr. Darcy, by the feelings which prevailed on his entering the room;
and then, though but a moment before she had believed her wishes to predominate, she began
to regret that he came.
He had been some time with Mr. Gardiner, who, with two or three other gentlemen from the
house, was engaged by the river; and had left him only on learning that the ladies of the
family intended a visit to Georgiana that morning.
No sooner did he appear, than Elizabeth wisely resolved to be perfectly easy and unembarrassed;—a
resolution the more necessary to be made, but perhaps not the more easily kept, because
she saw that the suspicions of the whole party were awakened against them, and that there
was scarcely an eye which did not watch his behaviour when he first came into the room.
In no countenance was attentive curiosity so strongly marked as in Miss Bingley’s,
in spite of the smiles which overspread her face whenever she spoke to one of its objects;
for jealousy had not yet made her desperate, and her attentions to Mr. Darcy were by no
means over.
Miss Darcy, on her brother’s entrance, exerted herself much more to talk; and Elizabeth saw
that he was anxious for his sister and herself to get acquainted, and forwarded, as much
as possible, every attempt at conversation on either side.
Miss Bingley saw all this likewise; and, in the imprudence of anger, took the first opportunity
of saying, with sneering civility,— “Pray, Miss Eliza, are not the ——shire
militia removed from Meryton?
They must be a great loss to your family.”
In Darcy’s presence she dared not mention Wickham’s name: but Elizabeth instantly
comprehended that he was uppermost in her thoughts; and the various recollections connected
with him gave her a moment’s distress; but, exerting herself vigorously to repel the ill-natured
attack, she presently answered the question in a tolerably disengaged tone.
While she spoke, an involuntary glance showed her Darcy with a heightened complexion, earnestly
looking at her, and his sister overcome with confusion, and unable to lift up her eyes.
Had Miss Bingley known what pain she was then giving her beloved friend, she undoubtedly
would have refrained from the hint; but she had merely intended to discompose Elizabeth,
by bringing forward the idea of a man to whom she believed her partial, to make her betray
a sensibility which might injure her in Darcy’s opinion, and, perhaps, to remind the latter
of all the follies and absurdities by which some part of her family were connected with
that corps.
Not a syllable had ever reached her of Miss Darcy’s meditated elopement.
To no creature had it been revealed, where secrecy was possible, except to Elizabeth;
and from all Bingley’s connections her brother was particularly anxious to conceal it, from
that very wish which Elizabeth had long ago attributed to him, of their becoming hereafter
her own.
He had certainly formed such a plan; and without meaning that it should affect his endeavour
to separate him from Miss Bennet, it is probable that it might add something to his lively
concern for the welfare of his friend.
Elizabeth’s collected behaviour, however, soon quieted his emotion; and as Miss Bingley,
vexed and disappointed, dared not approach nearer to Wickham, Georgiana also recovered
in time, though not enough to be able to speak any more.
Her brother, whose eye she feared to meet, scarcely recollected her interest in the affair;
and the very circumstance which had been designed to turn his thoughts from Elizabeth, seemed
to have fixed them on her more and more cheerfully.
Their visit did not continue long after the question and answer above mentioned; and while
Mr. Darcy was attending them to their carriage, Miss Bingley was venting her feelings in criticisms
on Elizabeth’s person, behaviour, and dress.
But Georgiana would not join her.
Her brother’s recommendation was enough to insure her favour: his judgment could not
err; and he had spoken in such terms of Elizabeth, as to leave Georgiana without the power of
finding her otherwise than lovely and amiable.
When Darcy returned to the saloon, Miss Bingley could not help repeating to him some part
of what she had been saying to his sister.
“How very ill Eliza Bennet looks this morning, Mr. Darcy,” she cried: “I never in my
life saw anyone so much altered as she is since the winter.
She is grown so brown and coarse!
Louisa and I were agreeing that we should not have known her again.”
However little Mr. Darcy might have liked such an address, he contented himself with
coolly replying, that he perceived no other alteration than her being rather tanned,—no
miraculous consequence of travelling in the summer.
“For my own part,” she rejoined, “I must confess that I never could see any beauty
in her.
Her face is too thin; her complexion has no brilliancy; and her features are not at all
handsome.
Her nose wants character; there is nothing marked in its lines.
Her teeth are tolerable, but not out of the common way; and as for her eyes, which have
sometimes been called so fine, I never could perceive anything extraordinary in them.
They have a sharp, shrewish look, which I do not like at all; and in her air altogether,
there is a self-sufficiency without fashion, which is intolerable.”
Persuaded as Miss Bingley was that Darcy admired Elizabeth, this was not the best method of
recommending herself; but angry people are not always wise; and in seeing him at last
look somewhat nettled, she had all the success she expected.
He was resolutely silent, however; and, from a determination of making him speak, she continued,—
“I remember, when we first knew her in Hertfordshire, how amazed we all were to find that she was
a reputed beauty; and I particularly recollect your saying one night, after they had been
dining at Netherfield, ‘She a beauty!
I should as soon call her mother a wit.’
But afterwards she seemed to improve on you, and I believe you thought her rather pretty
at one time.”
“Yes,” replied Darcy, who could contain himself no longer, “but that was only when
I first knew her; for it is many months since I have considered her as one of the handsomest
women of my acquaintance.”
He then went away, and Miss Bingley was left to all the satisfaction of having forced him
to say what gave no one any pain but herself.
Mrs. Gardiner and Elizabeth talked of all that had occurred during their visit, as they
returned, except what had particularly interested them both.
The looks and behaviour of everybody they had seen were discussed, except of the person
who had mostly engaged their attention.
They talked of his sister, his friends, his house, his fruit, of everything but himself;
yet Elizabeth was longing to know what Mrs. Gardiner thought of him, and Mrs. Gardiner
would have been highly gratified by her niece’s beginning the subject.